Okay, so בוקר טוב, boker tov, today we start on כג עמוד
ב, Chaf Gimmel Amud Bet, we'll try to do two today, דף
כו, Daf Chaf Vav, we'll try for that. Anyway, תנו רבנן Tanu
Rabbanan on כג עמוד ב Chaf Gimmel Amud Bet about 15 lines
from the bottom, two down. Line starts with the word שאין עליו
תשובה. she'ein alav teshuvah.
Okay. So we've been discussing different issues about wearing תפילין tefillin and
going to the bathroom, let's take a look. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan:
הרוצה ליכנס לסעודת קבע, Harotzeh likaneis liseudat keva, so if somebody wants
to go to a fixed meal, not like a snack but a
real serious sit-down dinner and banquet and you won't be able to
excuse yourself from the middle, it'll be embarrassing if you have to
excuse yourself to go to the bathroom. So what do you do?
מהלך עשרה פעמים ארבע אמות, Mehalek asara pe'amim arba amot, you go
take ten times four אמות, amot, four אמות amot is about six
feet. And according to רש״י, Rashi, at each one of these times
you try to go to the bathroom again. So, you know, when
you get up and you walk and you go back, sometimes it
helps you clear your bowels. So you do that ten times, או
ארבע פעמים י׳ אמות, o arba pe'amim yud amot, or four, or
for four times you walk ten אמות amot and then you try,
you try it then at each time. Why is this necessary for
the rabbis? Shouldn't people just go to the bathroom? Well remember yesterday
we said, remember yesterday we said that if you are a בעל
קרי ba'al keri you could learn הלכות דרך ארץ? hilchos derech eretz?
This is הלכות דרך ארץ. hilchos derech eretz. This is how do
you do so that you don't embarrass yourself and that you want
to be concerned about your dignity and take care of your business
before you sit down. I don't know, I understand, to me there's
something very beautiful about just
taking ordinary life, and people who are
going to be rabbis, to
take care of...
Okay, I hear that.
I hear
that concern.
It's a personality type for which that might reflect another way of
looking at it, is that civility in general is a religious value.
Exactly. And that an authentically religious person knows how to behave with
civility with a concern for the environment, the social environment in which
they are behaving.
No, you're right. You're right, but you can also see it as...
Right. Okay. So there are things that obviously you could interpret both
ways. All right. All right. Okay. It's a good point. I think
both of those are good points. Let's go on. אמר רב יצחק:
Amar Rav Yitzchak: הנכנס לסעודת קבע חולץ תפילין. Hanichnas liseudat keva choletz
tefillin.
Now we get to more הלכה. halacha. If you're about to sit
down to a meal, you take off your תפילין tefillin ואחר כך
נכנס ve’achar kach nichnas and then you go in. Why? What's the
concern? Well let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. ופליגי
דרבי חייא. U’pligi de’Rabbi Chiya. And this argues with Rabbi Chiya. דאמר
רבי חייא, De’amar Rabbi Chiya, Rabbi Chiya says, מניחין על שולחנו וכן
הדור לו. manichin al shulchano vechen hadur lo. You put it on,
so he agrees you take it off, but you don't leave it
on the outside, you can take it with you and put it
on your table and that is a like a glory to him.
Now what is the issue here? The issue here is that רש״י,
Rashi, if you look at רש״י Rashi five lines from the bottom,
רש״י Rashi says the concern is שמא ישתכר בתוך סעודתו ויתגנה בתפליו.
shema yishtacher betoch seudato veyitganeh bitfillav.
That maybe you'll get a little drunk and you'll act in an
improper way. It's interesting because you could have thought the concern was
maybe you'll pass gas, which tends to be a pretty common concern
with wearing תפילין. tefillin. And when the וכן הדור לו, vechen hadur
lo, why nice to have them near you? רש״י Rashi says משום
דמזמינו ויחזור ויניחם בשעת ברכה, mishum demazmino veyachzor veyanichun bish’at beracha,
that as we're about to see there's an idea of, you know
the practice some people have who wear black hats and then when
it's time for בענטשן benching they go and they get their jacket
on and their hat on, you ever see that? Anyway, we're going
to see something just like that with the תפילין. tefillin. So רש״י
Rashi says it's nice to have it right next to you so
you can put it on at the end of the meal when
it's time for בענטשן. benching. So let's see. Anyway what's fascinating here
is of course the sense the picture one gets of somebody wearing
תפילין tefillin the entire day and the only question is taking it
off when you're going into the bathroom, taking it off when you're
sitting down to a big meal. Okay, ועד אימת, ve’ad eimat, and
how long do you leave them off? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק:
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak: עד זמן
ברכה, Ad zman beracha, until the time for the ברכה, beracha, presumably
the ברכת המזון. Birkas Hamazon. תני חדא: Tani chada: צורר אדם תפליו
עם מעותיו באפרכסותו. Tzorer adam tefillav im me’otav be’afarkasuto. A person can
wrap, apparently this was some type of a of a head wrap
like some, some handkerchief or scarf that went around the head and
presumably for men and went down by the shoulders and you could
use some of the hanging material to wrap things in. So you
could use that head wrap to wrap both your תפילין tefillin in
it and your money in it. And it's not considered like something
that you have now turned into a wrapper for תפילין tefillin is
designated only for תפילין tefillin and cannot be used for other things.
We don't say that. ותני אידך, Vetani idach, and another ברייתא braita
says actually we do say that. לא יצור אדם, Lo yatzor adam,
that you cannot have it both for your a place use it
as a pouch for your money and for your תפילין. tefillin. And
we're not even talking about in the same like, you know, in
the same
space, even in different spaces, but using the same, using the same
cloth to the scarf to do both. So the גמרא Gemara says:
לא קשיא, Lo kashya, it's not a contradiction. הא דאזמניה הא דלא
אזמניה. Ha de’azmenei ha d’lo azmenei. The question is whether you've designated
it or not. This is a general question we have about when
something gets a certain הלכה halachic status. Whether it's like here, something's
going to be my תפילין tefillin bag, or you set aside something
to be used let's say for shrouds for a מת, meis, and
it becomes forbidden in benefit, or actually not. Not this גמרא, Gemara,
surprisingly, but other גמרא Gemara talks about if you set aside something
to be used as a בית הכסא, beis hakisei, as a bathroom,
does it, is it use that defines the status, is it designation,
is it the combination of the two? So here the גמרא Gemara
says when you have something that is your תפילין tefillin bag, your
wrapper for תפילין, tefillin, then it is doing a תשמיש קדושה, tashmish
kedusha, it is serving a holy object and cannot be used for
other things. But it's not enough that you happen to use something
once for that purpose. If you just once grabbed a, you know,
handkerchief and wrapped your תפילין, tefillin, it doesn't all of a sudden
become your תפילין tefillin bag, and you can use it for other
things as well. But if you designate it for such, that's an
issue. דאמר רב חסדא, D'amar Rav Chisda, because רב חסדא Rav Chisda
said, האי סודרא דתפילין, hai sudra d'tefillin, a certain scarf for תפילין,
tefillin, דאזמניה למצר ביה תפילין, d'azmanya l'meitzar bei tefillin, if you designated
it to wrap תפילין, tefillin, then designation is not enough either. You
need both designation and use. צר ביה תפילין, Tzar bei tefillin, אסור
למצר ביה זוזי, assur l'meitzar bei zuzei, once you've used it to
wrap תפילין, tefillin, you cannot use it to wrap
money. אזמניה ולא צר ביה, Azmanya v'lo tzar bei, if you designated
it and did not actually wrap the תפילין tefillin in it, or
wrap it around the תפילין. tefillin. צר ביה ולא אזמניה, Tzar bei
v'lo azmanya, you used it for your תפילין, tefillin, but you did
not designate it. שרי למצר ביה זוזי, shari l'meitzar bei zuzei, you
can use it to wrap money. Something only gets a status when
it's both designated and used. Okay, so that's one position. But actually
there's a classic debate of אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava about this point,
whether הזמנה, hazmana, designating something, is מילתא היא miltha hi or לאו
מילתא היא. lav miltha hi. Is, is a matter of import or
not? So here we're saying it is. It's not sufficient, but it's
necessary. So now the גמרא Gemara says ולאביי דאמר הזמנה מילתא היא,
U'l'Abaye d'amar hazmana miltha hi, now but אביי Abaye that says that
הזמנה hazmana by itself is significant. You don't need both designation and
use. Designation itself does the job. אזמניה, Azmanya, then if you designated
it, אף על גב דלא צר ביה, af al gav d'lo tzar
bei, even if you haven't used it for your תפילין, tefillin, it
becomes your status of a תפילין tefillin bag. צר ביה, Tzar bei,
and now if you, and if you wrapped it, that doesn't make
a difference. אי אזמניה אסירי, Ei azmanya asiri, even if you wrapped
it, it's only if you then designated it's forbidden. אי לא אזמניה
לא, Ei lo azmanya lo, and if you never wind up designating
it, then not. Of course you wonder like if you used it
for, you know, a year straight, at a certain point what does
designating mean? You know, are you thinking the words I hereby designate
it for my תפילין? tefillin? But okay, that's a separate question. But
nevertheless אביי Abaye says designating is enough and רב חסדא Rav Chisda
says you need both to designate and use. And this does tap
into גמרא Gemara a larger debate about when certain things, objects, get
their status and become forbidden for other types of use. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara says like this,
so we're moving thankfully at least for now a little way from
the bathroom, but this obviously you can see related topics. בעי מיניה
רב יוסף בריה דרב נחוניא מרב יהודה. Ba'ei minei Rav Yosef brei
d'Rav Nechunya mei'Rav Yehuda. So רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, the son of
רב נחוניא, Rav Nechunya, asked from רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, מהו שיניח
אדם תפילין תחת מראשותיו Mahu she'yanich adam tefillin tachat merashotav?
We said before you're not supposed to sleep with your תפילין tefillin
on. If you're, you're wearing it, then there's a concern you'll pass
gas. If you're not wearing it and you're holding it in your
hand, there's a concern you'll drop it. So you took your תפילין
tefillin off at nighttime. Can you put it underneath your head, under
your pillow? Okay, remember the whole question where are you keeping it.
So the גמרא Gemara says תחת מרגלותיו לא קמיבעיא לי, Tachat margalotav
lo kamiba'aya lei,
underneath his feet in his bed, that's not my question
because
that's treating them in a manner of disrespect. To have your תפילין
tefillin underneath your feet. כי קמיבעיא לי תחת מראשותיו, Ki kamiba'aya lei
tachat merashotav, under your pillow, right? Isn't that where you know you
store like special things under your, you know, under your head, under
your pillow? Maybe that's, that's respect, maybe that's okay. מאי, Mai, what's
the story? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said
to him, הכי אמר שמואל, Hachi amar Shmuel, here's what שמואל Shmuel
said, מותר אפילו אשתו עמו, mutar afillu ishto imo, it's permissible even
if his wife is with him. So even in the same bed
with husband and wife, presumably also other גמרות Gemaras make it clear
that husband and wife are naked together in the same bed, presumably
even if they're going to be having sex, it's okay, which is
a little bit surprising. So let's take a look where the גמרא
Gemara goes with this. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אפילו אשתו עמו. afillu
ishto imo. מיתיבי, Meitivei,
I'll ask you on this. לא יניח אדם תפילין תחת מרגלותיו, Lo
yanich adam tefillin tachat margalotav, מפני שנוהג בהן מנהג ביזיון. mipnei she'noheig
bahen minhag bizayon.
You should not put your תפילין tefillin under your legs, under your
feet, because that is a sign of disrespect. אבל מניחן תחת מראשותיו,
Aval manichan tachat merashotav,
you can put them underneath your head. ואם הייתה אשתו עמו, V'im
hayta ishto imo, but if it's a man who's with his wife
in bed, then אסור, assur, that's forbidden. Now it goes on it
says היה מקום שגבוה ג' טפחים, Haya makom she'gavoha gimmel tefachim, או
נמוך ג' טפחים, o namuch gimmel tefachim, מותר. mutar. Even if it
is a place that is, that is higher than three טפחים tefachim
off the bed, it's like a shelf higher than three טפחים tefachim
from his head, that's considered somehow to be in a separate space,
which is interesting. You'd think they're still in the same room, who
cares if it's three טפחים tefachim off the bed. Or if it
is lower than three טפחים, tefachim, which we'll see later you know,
either way it's also like somehow away from him, and we'll talk
later about being under the bed and the bed is low so
it might be considered buried in that case, then it is permissible.
permissible. So it's a little surprising once it's a problem that putting
it on a higher shelf is okay. But anyway, the first point
here is that here it's clear that it cannot be when husband
and wife are together. So the Gemara says תיובתא דשמואל תיובתא, Tiyuvta
d'Shmuel tiyuvta, so that is a full contradiction of Shmuel's position, it
is not accepted with husband and wife together, which sort of makes
sense. You were wondering what Shmuel was thinking unless he thought that
underneath a pillow was considered to some degree like it was buried.
We'll talk about that later, how the Gemara says it's okay if
it's a low bed and it's under the bed. Under a low
bed with like a low
rise, anyway, that's like it's buried in the ground, it's like it's
not even there. So maybe Shmuel was thinking something similar and here
the Gemara says no, it's not considered like it's not there and
therefore it's a problem if husband and wife will be together. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, but now Rava says אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אף
על גב דתניא תיובתא דשמואל, af al gav d'tanya tiyuvta d'Shmuel, although
the brayta is a contradiction to Shmuel, הלכתא כוותיה, hilchata kevatei, we
rule like him. So which is pretty shocking. Sometimes the Gemara does
it as two steps. First this תיובתא tiyuvta to so-and-so תיובתא, tiyuvta,
and then either right afterwards or sometimes maybe a page later
it says הלכתא hilchata like this. תיובתא והלכתא? Tiyuvta vehilchata?
You contradict him and then you're ruling like him? And then it
goes on here, Rava's already incorporating that point. I know we contradicted
him, we're still going to rule like him. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama,
why? דף כג עמוד א, Daf chof gimel amud aleph, כל
נטירותא טפי עדיף, kol netiruta tfei adif, anything to protect them is
more important. So you can see an analogy from what we said
yesterday, the same way we let the guy hold them in the
bathroom because in order to protect them even though that was obviously
very
inappropriate, but it was allowed for protecting them. Here it is allowed
to keep something under your pillow is something that's protected and therefore
it is allowed. Of course the difference is before it was like
occasionally you have to go to the bathroom with your tefillin on,
there's nowhere to put it. Here presumably it's every night and nevertheless
maybe not every night husband and wife are together, but it's still,
we're still going to allow it because it allows for greater protection
of the
tefillin. והיכא מנח להו, Veheicha manach lehu, and now it's going to
be under your head, where is it going to be under your
head? אמר רבי ירמיה בין כר לכסת, Amar Rabbi Yirmeyah bein kar
lechesset, between the pillow and the
blanket, שלא כנגד ראשו, shelo keneged rosho, but not directly, like your
head is not resting on top of the tefillin, it's under the
pillow but off to the side of your head. Which again makes
sense, it's more respectful than actually putting your head straight on the
tefillin. והתניא רבי חייא, Vehatanya Rabbi Chiya, doesn't Rabbi Chiya teach מניחין
בכובע תחת מראשותיו, manichin bekova tachat merashotav, that you put them in
sort of
under a hat underneath your head, meaning that the way the Gemara
assumes it means is like there's a bump, you put them in
and they create a bump, a hump, and your head is directly
sort of on the hump, that's what the Gemara understands.
Rashi says כובע kova here means
their bag. Anyway, it sounds like it's directly under your head. So
the Gemara says
we haven't said that yet, no, we haven't said that yet, but
it basically is saying is, so here it sounds like you're using
the tefillin bag as a type of a pillow, right? Or it's
not clear actually, but you're right, is it getting to the point
that you need a bag and under your pillow? But anyway, this
brayta says you put them in the bag and under your head.
So again it sounds like if your head is on the bag
then you're directly on top of the tefillin. It's not just saying
the tefillin are under the pillow, the tefillin are in the bag
and your head's on the bag. דמפקי ליה למורשא דכובא לבר, Damafki
lei lemorsha dechova levar,
no, you sort of take out the corner, the edge of the
tefillin outside. So you can have a bag, can I use this
as an example? This is your tefillin bag, right? So the bump
can be in the middle, but your bag can be under your
head, but here the corner, like the bump, is away from my
head and my head is here. So the same idea as the
pillow. Yes, your head is on the bag and the bag has
the tefillin in it, but it doesn't mean that your head is
on top of the tefillin. Okay, so thank you. So now the
Gemara says בר קפרא צייר להו בכילתא ומפיק למורשיהן לבר, Bar Kappara
tzayar lehu bechilta u'mafik lemorsheihen levar, Bar Kappara wrapped them in the
כילתא kilta and taking the corners out. Bar Kappara wrapped them in
the כילתא, kilta, the כילתא chilta is the canopy that they had
over a bed. So presumably he wrapped them using the material of
the canopy, but presumably
he
still, it was like a lot of material, he wanted it also
still under his head to protect it, so near him. So he
wrapped it in the canopy
but he kept the bump on the outside. This also might mean
that if you look at Rashi also might mean that he wasn't
doing it under his head, but he didn't want the bump of
the tefillin facing towards the inside of the bed, it's a greater
respect keeping the tefillin, the bump pointing away from the bed. So
if you look at Rashi, the first narrow line, בליטת הקשר של
תפילין בולטין מן היריעה היה הופך לצד החוץ ולא לצד המיטה. Belitat
hakesher shel tefillin boltin min hayeria hayah hofech letzad hachutz v'lo letzad
hamitah.
So then it's somewhat different, it's not the point of not putting
your head directly on the tefillin, it's more the point of like
it's again somewhat of an analogy of what we talked yesterday, was
the tefillin on the side of the wall facing the bathroom or
the side of the wall facing the street. So here he wrapped
them. wrapped the תפילין tfillin in these, in the canopy, you know,
the curtains around his bed, and he had the bump facing outside,
which was more respectful. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
רב ששת בריה דרב אידי Rav Sheshet Bereih deRav Idi מנח להו
אהששיפא. manach lehu ahashshifa. He kept his תפילין tfillin on a stool
in his room, ופריש סודרא עלוייה, uforesh sudra ilvaye, and he put—oh
you okay? אוי אוי. oy oy. All right, there. Okay. And he
put a scarf, a handkerchief on top of it. So again, it
wasn't directly under his head in the bed.
It might have
been in the
bedroom, but it was on some nightstand and was covered. אמר רב
המנונא בריה דרב יוסף, Amar Rav Hamnuna Bereih deRav Yosef, זימנא חדא
הוה יתיבנא קמיה דרבא. Zimna chada hava yatvina kammai deRava. So רב
המנונא Rav Hamnuna said, "One time I was in front of רבא,
Rava, ואמר לי, v'amar li, 'זיל אייתי לי תפילין.' Zil aiti li
tfillin. Go get me my תפילין. tfillin. Okay, they're in my room."
ואשכחתינהו בין כר לכסת, v'ashkachitinhu bein kared lekhisat, and I was looking
around for them and I found the תפילין, tfillin, and where were
they? They were between the pillow and the blanket, שלא כנגד ראשו,
shelo kineged rosho, in the place where not directly where his head
would lay. I don't know how he could tell, maybe there was
an
indentation in the
pillow, so I found it exactly there like we had said before.
ואידנא דיום טבילה הוה. V'aydana d'yom tevila hava. I figured out
it was the night his wife went to the
מקווה, mikvah, ואגמרא והלכה למעשה הוא דעבד. v'agamra v'halacha lema'aseh hu de'avad.
And or I happened to know, maybe, that it was when his
wife was going to the מקווה mikvah and he was teaching me
a הלכה. halacha. He wanted to show me that even if a
husband and wife are together in bed, that you can keep the
תפילין tfillin under the head, just not right, not directly, you know,
not lay your head on top of it, but under the pillow
even if they're together in bed. So, by the way, what is
interesting here is the fact that in passing we're assuming that it's
saying that the night that the wife comes back from the מקווה
mikvah they're having sex. Obviously we know in הלכה halacha that is
treated as a night where it's a מצווה mitzvah for husband and
wife to be together, but the גמרא Gemara sort of never really
formally comes out and straight states that. It just assumes it in
passing, and that's actually quite important because, you know, רב משה פיינשטיין
Rav Moshe Feinstein discusses, you know, the basic principle is—is that it's
a מצווה mitzvah to have sex when—well, for the husband's obligation of
עונה onah when—when his wife is desirous. And there's an assumption that
that's true when she's coming back from the מקווה. mikvah. But if
that's not the case, you know, sometimes it's a little bit quick
for—you know, quick to go from having been totally—totally separate to then
being immediately together. So there's not a particular מצווה mitzvah on the
night of the מקווה, mikvah, only
it's based only on the circumstances and based on the assumption that
that's when the wife is very much desirous of it. So the
גמרא Gemara sort of assumes it in passing, but
that is a strict obligation of that night. Yes. Why would he
ask for the תפילין? tfillin? That's—yes, to go and to take the
תפילין tfillin out of the bed. Right. Because—because I'm going to be
with my wife tonight. Yeah, the assumption seemed to have been that
they were—that he was wanting his תפילין tfillin because he wanted to
put them on. And, you know, it seems like the חידוש chiddush
here is that all of the project—I mean, how did he know
to learn it or how do I know I'm reading the גמרא
Gemara correctly? You're right, because you could
read the גמרא Gemara
like he's saying he wanted to show me so that I got
to get the תפילין tfillin out because he's going to be with
his wife the following night as opposed to he was with his
wife the previous night and he was showing me where he kept
his תפילין tfillin the previous night. So I suppose there's some ambiguity
how to read the גמרא. Gemara. First of all, I'm following רש"י.
Rashi. Second of all, the details here, בין כר לכסת שלא כנגד
ראשו, bein kared lekhisat shelo kineged rosho, exactly parallel what we just
ruled before according to שמואל. Shmuel. And that previous ruling of שמואל
Shmuel included the idea even when husband and wife are together. So
it seems that since גמרא, Gemara, you know, that it's coming to
reinforce, not to challenge. But yeah, you could read it that way.
רש"י Rashi seems to—רש"י Rashi reads it that they had sex the
prior night and he was showing me where the—or assumes that—and they
were showing me where the תפילין tfillin were. Yes. Is it because
you think it's happening during the day? If it's in the morning
and he's taking the תפילין tfillin to put them on. If it's
at night, how does he have them on all day? So the
only thing, take them off and put them under the pillow, and
then he'd say to his student, "Go and get them for me,
I forgot I left them under my pillow"
after—I don't know why he'd have to go after sundown. So, I
mean, it's the same thing, in other words, you read this like
it's in the morning, you read this as after sundown. Right. I
thought the whole point of keeping the תפילין tfillin under the head
was for protection. Yeah. So how can he leave his תפילין tfillin
under...?
If the whole point is that it's supposed to be protected.
That's an interesting question. That's a good question. What did he get
up in the morning, what's he doing leaving them in his bedroom
if
you need to keep them there to protect them? I don't know,
it's a very good question. It's a very good question. All right.
I mean, you could say things like, okay, maybe just being in
the bedroom was protected, but then why is it under the head?
Right. All right, yes. Very good question. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says, בעי מיניה רב יוסף בריה דרב נחוניא מרב יהודה.
bei minei Rav Yosef Bereih deRav Nachuniah meRav Yehuda. So רב יוסף
Rav Yosef the son of נחוניא Nachuniah asked from רב יהודה: Rav
Yehuda: שנים שישנים במיטה אחת מהו שזה יחזיר פניו ויקרא קריאת שמע
וזה יחזיר פניו ויקרא קריאת
שמע? Shnayim sheyishenin bemitah achat mahu shezeh yachzir panav veyikra krias shema
vezeh yachzir panav veyikra krias shema? Now we get to—again, all
these are obviously related. Proper ways of storing your תפילין, tfillin, you
know, but we sort of... moved from bathroom issues to husband and
wife being together, nakedness and similar concerns. That's just storing them in
the bedroom. So now we're going to get to this discussion about,
and this is a key גמרא Gemara when we get later to
the דף daf you'll all know the גמרא Gemara that we're that
we're going that we're going to be reading, about how to define,
you know, sort of nakedness in the context of דאבנינג, davening, שמע
Shema related types of issues where it would be obviously inappropriate to
be דאבנינג davening or saying שמע Shema when one is naked or
in front of a person who is naked. So here the question
is the following: what was the הלכה? halacha? You have two people
in a bed, doesn't necessarily assume husband and wife, could be two
brothers are sharing a bed, you know, they didn't have a lot
of room in those days, people shared beds. So what if, what's
the story if one person, and they might be naked in the
bed, you know, pajamas wasn't necessarily the case either. So what is
the story that if one person turns his face one direction and
the other turns his face the other direction, so they're back to
back, so can they say קריאת שמע? krias shema? So they're sort
of naked but they're not facing each other, their genitals are not
touching, and we're assuming that you can be naked under a blanket
by yourself and say the שמע. Shema. Remember the משנה mishna said
that you can be in a מקוה mikvah and your head is
outside of the water and that's okay. So we're going to get
to that discussion later about, you know, about whether you need to
have a belt, how about you know what's the story about about
your, can you be naked under a blanket and say שמע? Shema?
But the assumption here is yes. Yes. Totally.
A custom up until about 150 years ago was travelers at inns
would share beds. Aha.
Right. Okay. There you go. Period. Right, but but of course there
I assume people were wearing pajamas. They were wearing day clothes. Day
clothes. Yeah.
Okay. So anyway, but here it's assuming that people are naked under
the bed.
Maybe again, it was brothers or something of that nature. So מהו
שזה יחזיר פניו ויקרא קריאת שמע? mahu she-zeh yachzir panav ve-yikra krias
shema? This one turned face one way and זה יחזיר פניו ויקרא
קריאת שמע, zeh yachzir panav ve-yikra krias shema, the other one turned
the other way. Also because presumably if you're going to be דאבנינג
davening שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei presumably you're standing up. But שמע Shema
you're lying in bed, maybe you just woke up, it's about to
be sunrise, we went before with that some face after sunrise you
can't say it. What's the story there? It's nighttime שמע Shema you
remember. אמר ליה הכי אמר שמואל. amar lei hachi amar Shmuel. Here's
what שמואל Shmuel says: אפילו אשתו עמו. afilu ishto imo. We're going
to make a parallel. שמואל Shmuel allows you to have תפילין tefillin
in the room where husband and wife are together naked and maybe
even having sex, so presumably he wouldn't have a problem with this.
So obviously there's a little bit of a difference. So the גמרא
Gemara says and the גמרא Gemara here now, one way I'm reading
it is that we're sort of looking at שמואל Shmuel as an
analogy from what he said over there, אפילו אשתו עמו. afilu ishto
imo. רש״י Rashi says that שמואל Shmuel actually said that exact statement
by the case of שמע, Shema, not an analogy to the תפילין,
tefillin, but exactly he ruled that way by the שמע. Shema. רש״י
Rashi says ואפילו אשתו עמו שיחזיר פניו. va-afilu ishto imo she-yachzir panav.
Okay, so רש״י Rashi says that שמואל's Shmuel's ruling was שמואל Shmuel
says it's okay for saying שמע, Shema, husband and wife back to
back. So if husband and wife can do it, certainly two strangers.
That's sort of the assumption. אפילו afilu even, even a man's own
wife you can do it where presumably there's more sexual thoughts and
so on, so all the more so two strangers can do it.
So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב יוסף, maskif lah Rav
Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks on this: אשתו ולא מיבעיא אחר?
ishto velo mibaya acher? You say a man can do it with
his wife and goes without saying with somebody else it's okay? That
I don't think that makes sense. אדרבה, aderaba, the opposite makes sense.
אשתו כגופו, ishto k-gufo, a man's wife is like his body. אחר
לאו כגופו, acher lav k-gufo, somebody else is not like his body.
Which means that, you know, you could translate this in formal terms
or in just sort of, you know, sort of psychological terms. רש״י
Rashi says the latter. רש״י Rashi says a man, you know, who
husband and wife who have been married together, yeah they're attracted to
one another, but it's not like a unusual event, so it's possible
that they could be doing this and it could not be getting
them too sexually excited. But where somebody else, you know, we are
concerned more for arousal. Again assuming it's funny because it's not, it's
not assuming a man and a woman who are not married are
in bed together. It's presumably two men. And nevertheless, we're more concerned
with the possibility of arousal. If you look at רש״י, Rashi, אשתו
כגופו, ishto k-gufo, he says ורגיל בה ולא אתי להרהורי כולי האי.
ve-ragil bah velo ati le-hirhurei kulei hai. Right. So again, it's, you
know, it does speak about the fact that, you know, that this
type of an experience can evoke erotic thoughts. Yes, so
so why isn't why isn't this approach applied to the הרחקות harchakos
today? Well, okay, that's an interesting question that gets to the larger,
you know we sort of actually I was going to say we
discussed it when we did נדה, Niddah, but not really, because that
specific topic comes up in שבת. Shabbos. So we'll get to it
in about three two months. But the short answer is that, well,
okay, the short answer there's a couple of answers, but the quick
and easy answer is is that there you're talking about a case
where it's חייב כרת, chayav kares, so if one thing leads to
another and they have sex, it's a pretty heavy problem. Whereas here,
it's just a question about two minutes and saying the שמע, Shema,
so the level of concerns is different. I mean, there's other differences
as well, we'll get... more when we learn the topic in שבת,
Shabbat, which is coming up in about two months. So that's the
answer. Now, it could also be a different formalistic difference, which is
if I'm under the bed and I'm covered with a blanket, even
though I'm naked under the blanket, I can—it's not considered a problem
for me to be with my own nudity. You know, again, if
I wasn't covered, it would be a problem, but if it's under
a blanket, it's okay. So אשתו כגופו ishtu k'gufo could be a
formal answer, if it's considered to be, you know, not somebody else's
nudity, but essentially your own, and it's all under the blanket, it's
okay. So that's not about the question about sexual thoughts at all,
right? It's—but it's a question about the appropriateness of being under the
same blanket with somebody else who's naked. And how much do we
look at husband and wife as the same or as different? So
that's a more formal reading. רש״י Rashi reads it, it's all about
sexual thoughts, and then it's interesting because it's a case of presumably
two men, and there's a concern of erotic thoughts. Yes.
How do we know that the גמרא Gemara is assuming that there's
a blanket?
I—well,
it's—well,
you could also say how do we know the גמרא Gemara is
assuming that they're
naked? The general—I mean, if there's no blanket and they're naked, then
obviously nobody's saying שמע Shema even if nobody else is around.
And the assumption of naked—I mean, רש״י Rashi says it, but in
general the גמרא Gemara assumes that people are sleeping in the nude.
I mean, you see that in other סוגיות sugyot that the גמרא
Gemara assumes that. But you're right, I mean, it's not explicit. Okay,
so let's take a look.
So the ברייתא baraita says like this: מיתיבי, Meiteivei, it asks: שנים
שישנים במיטה אחת, shnayim sheyeshenim bemitah achat, if you have two people
in one bed, זה מחזיר פניו וקורא וזה מחזיר פניו וקורא. zeh
machzir panav vekorei vezeh machzir panav vekorei. So each one you can
turn—turn back to back and read, which is—which seems to be, again,
even not a man and wife, that's okay, supporting what we said
before. ותניא אידך, Vetanya idach, but in another ברייתא baraita it says:
הישן במיטה ובניו ובני ביתו בצידו, hayashen bemitah uvanav uvnei veito betzido,
if somebody is sleeping in a bed, and here you can see
it's a family thing, and your kids and בני ביתו, bnei veito,
which are not just your kids, you know, whatever, the people, the
guests of your house, are all sleeping in the same bed, הרי
זה לא יקרא קריאת שמע, harei zeh lo yikra krias Shema, אלא
אם כן הייתה טלית מפסקת ביניהם. ela im kein haytah tallis mafsekes
beineihem.
You can't say שמע Shema unless you use some type of a
garment to serve as some like divider along the bed, you know,
maybe between—you know, so it's—it's lying vertically to separate the bodies. That's
okay. But if the bodies are touching, it's not okay. So what's
the story? Is it okay or not okay? So the גמרא Gemara
says: בשלמא לרב יוסף, bishlama l'Rav Yosef, according to רב יוסף Rav
Yosef who distinguishes between wife and other people, לא קשיא. la kashya.
הא באשתו, ha beishto, where do we say that it's okay? A
husband and wife. הא באחר, ha beacher, the other case is other
people, you know, maybe even—even your kids—even children. I mean, you know,
obviously we know about the concerns about sexual abuse, you know, of
child abuse and so on. So people do have erotic thoughts, and
there it says בני ביתו, bnei veito, even not relatives. So when
it's a man's wife, we're not concerned; when it's other people, we
are concerned. אלא לשמואל קשיא. ela l'Shmuel kashya. But according to
שמואל Shmuel it's difficult. שמואל Shmuel said it's okay with anybody as
long as you're back to back. So why does this ברייתא baraita
say it's a problem? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר לך שמואל,
amar lach Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel will say to you: ורב יוסף
מי ניחא, veRav Yosef mi nicha, what makes it so good according
to רב יוסף? Rav Yosef? You wanted to say that where it's
okay is wife and where it's not okay is everybody else. והתניא,
vehatanya, a ברייתא baraita says: הישנים במיטה ובני ביתו במיטה לא יקרא
קריאת שמע אלא אם כן הייתה טלית מפסקת
ביניהם, hayeshenim bemitah uvnei veito bemitah lo yikra krias Shema ela im
kein haytah tallis mafsekes beineihem, that don't—if you have other people with
you in the bed, don't say שמע Shema unless there's a טלית
tallis dividing you. And רש״י Rashi says somehow we assume that that
also includes one's wife, although it's not so clear why. But anyway,
תוספות Tosafot has the גרסה: girsa: הישן במיטה ואשתו עמו. hayashen bemitah
veishto imo.
Somehow שמואל Shmuel had a ברייתא baraita that said even explicitly that
even with a husband and wife cannot be saying שמע. Shema. So
we've got a problem with the ברייתות baraitas regardless. אלא מאי אית
לך למימר, ela mai is lach leimar, אשתו לרב יוסף תנאי היא.
ishto l'Rav Yosef tannai hi. רב
יוסף Rav Yosef would say, okay, there are some תנאים Tannaim that
say husband and wife can't be doing it, but I don't—there are
other תנאים Tannaim that say they can, and I go like the
others. ואחרים נמי תנאי. vaacherim nami tannai. So I also admit there
are some תנאים Tannaim that say you can't do it with other
people, and I say whether it's a man's wife or whether it's
other people, as long as you're back to back, it's okay. So
we have here a debate, but at least everybody agrees husband and
wife can be naked under the blanket back to back and saying
שמע. Shema. Pretty shocking, right? And then שמואל Shmuel goes so far
to include in that even other people. Okay, so that's when it's
all—so let's keep on going. So אמר מר, amar mar, let's look
at what we've just quoted before. זה מחזיר פניו וקורא קריאת שמע.
zeh machzir panav vekorei krias Shema. So you can turn—turn your backs
to one another and say שמע. Shema. והא איכא עגבות, veha ika
agavos,
so the גמרא Gemara is saying, okay, it's very nice that the
genitals aren't touching, but how about the buttocks? They're touching and maybe
those are considered to be also ערווה. ervah. This is a question
what is considered ערווה ervah for the גמרא. Gemara. So—nakedness. So גמרא
Gemara says: מסייע ליה לרב הונא. mesayei leh l'Rav Huna. This supports
רב הונא. Rav Huna. דאמר רב הונא: deamar Rav Huna: עגבות אין
בהם משום ערווה, agavos ein bahem mishum ervah, buttocks is not considered
to be ערווה. ervah. לימא מסייע ליה לרב הונא, leima mesayei leh
l'Rav Huna, let's come to support it. האישה יושבת וקוצה חלתה ערומה,
haishah yosheves vekotzah challatah arumah,
a woman can sit and be naked and separate חלה challah and
make a ברכה, bracha, מפני שיכולה לכסות פניה
בקרקע. mipnei sheyecholah lechasos paneiha bakarka. her face, it's a euphemism, right,
her genitals can be covered in the ground. אבל לא האיש, aval
lo ha'ish, not a man, because if you're sitting and you're naked,
your genitals are exposed and therefore you can't make a ברכה bracha
in that state. So the גמרא Gemara says, so you see, what
about the buttocks? It seems that buttocks isn't the problem. תרגמה רב
נחמן בר יצחק, Targemah Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, כגון שהיו פניה טוחות
בקרקע. kegon she'hayu paneha tuchot b'karka.
No, it could be a case that she's so flattened down and
pressed down that even her buttocks isn't exposed, maybe it is a
problem. Now, you have to take a step back and understand that
there are two categories in הלכה halacha relating to ערוה. ervah. One
has to do with just the presence of ערוה ervah when you
are saying ברכות brachot or שמע Shema or so on. That is
a problem even if it's your own nakedness. Okay, it's not a
problem that you're having sexual thoughts, it's just a problem that you
don't say ברכות brachot in the presence of nakedness, even your own
nakedness, right? So here the person, a person naked making a ברכה
bracha and so on. There's other questions the גמרא Gemara is going
to get to about ליבו רואה את הערוה, libo ro'eh et ha'ervah,
maybe, you know, you know, can you have if the, if it
covers your entire body but there's nothing between, you know, between
your torso and and you know and the lower area, maybe that's
not enough also, maybe it has to, you need a belt or
something, we'll talk about that. But minimally, right, you cannot be making
a ברכה bracha naked. You've got to be covered with the blanket
or you've got to be in the מקוה mikvah and your head
outside of the מקוה. mikvah. That's even your own nakedness. For that
the גמרא Gemara says the only definition of ערוה ervah is the
genitals, right? Secondary, you know, as you know, for women even the
breasts don't count, the buttocks don't count, only the genitals. If every
if the, if the genitals are covered and everything else is exposed
and you're in a room by yourself, you can actually make a
ברכה. bracha. That's the הלכה, halacha, that's the only thing that's an
ערוה. ervah. Then there's a second problem of if you are with
seeing somebody else's body that arouses you and then that's a problem
about arousal, and we're going to get to that in a minute,
that's the famous גמרא Gemara about שער באשה ערוה sear b'isha ervah
and so on. And that's an issue which is a much broader
definition and is really much more of a function of what arouses
you. So objectively it's only the genitals, what arouses you is much
broader. So the גמרא's Gemara's question here is, seems to be the
following. Okay, I get we're not concerned about arousal. But isn't there
a problem that if you're in the bed naked with this other
person, but isn't there the objective problem that there is ערוה ervah
here? The buttocks is being touching and you're touching ערוה ervah although
it's covered, maybe it's nevertheless touching. I'll give you an example. Let's
say you had your own genitals covered but you were touching them
when you were making a ברכה. bracha. Obviously that's wrong. So if
part of your body is touching somebody else's ערוה, ervah, that could
be a problem. That's the גמרא's Gemara's question. But again, it's important
to distinguish between objective ערוה ervah where exposure or touching is an
issue and then things that cause sexual thoughts, which is a much
broader category. The גמרא's Gemara's answer is objective ערוה ervah is only
the genitals. Yes, Dove. I have two questions.
One is, you just said something about the valence of the word
ערוה, ervah, that is to say תועבה to'evah is implicitly a pejorative
or negative word. Right. Is ערוה, ervah, should we read that word
in any way with a negative valence or is it an objective
description of a person's not covered? Right, right.
So it's clear that ערוה ervah often has very negative, like, like,
you know, איסורי עריות, issurei arayot, right, are the things that are
forbidden. Of course there's מאכלות אסורות, ma'achalot asurot, right, and מאכל ma'achal
is not a problematic word, right? The איסורי עריות issurei arayot is
the fact that they are אסור. assur. The עריות arayot are sexual
acts and maybe the word itself is not, doesn't have a valence.
But nevertheless, you know, and the תורה Torah speaks about, you know,
uncovering the ערוה ervah of a woman that a man is forbidden
to. But again, it's a problem because she's forbidden to him. It's
not the ערוה ervah itself, you know, means sort of, you know,
has to do with nakedness and sex and so on is, one
could definitely argue that it is a non-valenced word, it's often in
the context of forbidden ערוה, ervah, but, you know, it is true
we tend to assume that there's a negativity associated with it. The
גמרא's Gemara's use of it here as we're going to see is
that the basis of saying that you don't say ברכות brachot or,
you know, דאוון daven in the presence of ערוה ervah is the
פסוק pasuk of ולא יראה בך ערות דבר. v'lo yera'eh b'cha ervat
davar. When the תורה Torah talks about you go out to war
and you go and you, you know, you you do the bathroom
outside of the camp and the nakedness is not seen amongst you
and God will return, you know, will sort of remove God's self
from you. So there the, it's not seeing
ערות דבר ervat davar present with דאוונינג, davening, with שמע, Shema, so
that's where it's learned from. Of course you could say, okay, that
פסוק pasuk says God and ערוה ervah don't go together and there's
something negative about that. But there's also something very natural about that.
The guy goes to the bathroom, you know, people have sex and
so on. So I don't know. I think that, I think in
this context it's dealt with as a strictly הלכתי halachic matter. You
cannot דאוון daven in the presence of ערוה. ervah. You cannot say
שמע Shema in the presence of ערוה, ervah, you know, and and
so on. And I don't see an, I don't see it here
in a negative valence. Okay, so that is what the גמרא Gemara
says about the issue about the buttocks. So now we go on.
אמר מר, amar mar, היו בניו ובני ביתו קטנים, hayu banav u'vnei
beito ktanim, if your children were minor, מותר, mutar, then it's okay.
So with your with your with your with your small kids. So
interesting גמרא Gemara considering as I said as what we know about
issues about about sexual abuse, the גמרא Gemara says
עד כמה, ad kama, until what age? Meaning the גמרא Gemara clearly
assumes that after a certain age it would be
inappropriate. So it says עד כמה, ad kama, אמר רב פפא, amar
Rav Pappa, תינוקת בת שלוש שנים ויום אחד ותינוק בן תשע שנים
ויום אחד. tinokes bas shalosh shanim veyom echad vetinok ben tesha shanim
veyom echad. First of all, it doesn't distinguish, well it does distinguish
age between boys and girls, but it does distinguish in thinking there's
something problematic about a man sleeping with his kids. It recognizes that
after a certain point it's a problem whether his child is a
daughter or a son. But again, the first answer is that it
has to do with the technical age of when we say you
know something would be considered a sexual act. So with the girls
it would be three years old, with the boys it would be
nine years old. Now that is more of a formal type of
a distinction, doesn't really explain you know the concerns about about people's
יצר הרע. yetzer hara. So that's the next answer of the גמרא.
Gemara. איכא דאמרי, ika damri, others say, תינוקת בת אחת עשרה שנה
ויום אחד ותינוק בן שתים עשרה שנה ויום אחד, tinokes bas achas
esreh shanah veyom echad vetinok ben shtem esreh shanah veyom echad, starting
a year before puberty. A girl eleven and a day, a boy
twelve and a day when they are starting to show some sexual
characteristics. שנאמר, shene'emar, עדי ועד עד כדי שדדים נכונו ושערך צמח, adi
va'ad ad kedei shedadayim nachonu use'arech tzimayach, until when they get start
getting into the category of the פסוק pasuk from יחזקאל Yechezkel that
the sort of the breasts are you know are ripe and the
hair is sprouting forth, the pubic hair. Meaning so when they're starting
to show some signs of their body of sexual maturity, there is
then a concern that they're it is inappropriate for them to be
in the same bed with a parent, even with a same-sex parent.
And that's and now the question is is it inappropriate in general,
or is it just inappropriate if you want to be saying שמע?
Shema? Because if you're saying the שמע, Shema, then there's a concern
again about you know sort of sexual thoughts and so on. It's
not so clear from the גמרא Gemara you know which which is
the case.
But it's interesting that it refers first to a three-year-old girl as
an object.
Right. Well that we know the גמרא Gemara does some, but the
second one at least here is more realistic. If you look at
רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi seems to be that the concern here is
not just for שמע, Shema, it's about generally whether they should be
in the same bed. רש״י Rashi says בת אחת עשרה ובן שתים
עשרה זמן שהן באות לכלל שערות ושדיים נכונו שמשם ואילך באות לכלל
ביאה שאדם מתאוה להן. bas achas esreh uven shtem esreh zman shehen
ba'os likhlal se'aros veshadayim nachonu shemisham ve'eilach ba'os likhlal bi'ah she'adam misaveh
lahen. Right. But the בת שלוש bas shalosh he says is זמן
שהן באות לכלל ביאה. zman shehen ba'os likhlal bi'ah. Right. And here
he's saying that's in a formalistic way, but here it's a time
when when there could be actual sort of sexual desire.
But people
could be aroused by three.
I know, but the shift in the גמרא Gemara there it's
a technically an act
of sex, but if you talk about arousal and desire, that seems
to be this other opinion.
You told me we were talking about being naked. Right. What about
sleeping with קטנים? ketanim?
Yeah, so the גמרא's Gemara generally assuming being naked. It's not getting
into that question if they're not, right, and presumably you know that
could very well be a very different case. So but right here
the assumption is being naked. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
אמר ליה רב כהנא לרב אשי התם אמר רבא amar lei Rav
Kahana le-Rav Ashi hasam amar Rava back there when we were talking
about the תפילין tefillin under your head, רבא Rava said אף על
גב דתיופתא דשמואל הלכתא כוותיה דשמואל. af al gav detyufta di-Shmuel hilchasa
kevaseih di-Shmuel. Although שמואל Shmuel has been contradicted, we rule like שמואל,
Shmuel, you keep the תפילין tefillin under your head because we're concerned
about them being protected. הכא מאי? hacha mai? What's the story here?
Do we rule like שמואל Shmuel that you can be in bed
with another person back to back and it's not an issue? So
the גמרא Gemara says, right, הכא מאי? hacha mai? So אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said to him, אטו כולהו בחדא מחיתא מחתינהו? atu
kuleihu be-chada machisa machsinhu? What, you think they're all woven together? היכא
דאתמר אתמר והיכא דלא אתמר לא אתמר. heicha de-isamar isamar ve-heicha de-lo
isamar lo isamar. Where it was said, it was said; where it
wasn't said, it wasn't said. Which means we don't necessarily rule like
שמואל Shmuel in this case. Maybe it is a problem back to
back, a man with somebody else. He's not clearly ruling against him,
but he's saying you can't assume we rule like him. Okay. Now
we
so we've talked about with somebody else, but we've introduced the idea
of ערוה, erva, and I've mentioned to you ערוה erva is a
problem even if it's yourself, your own ערוה erva being uncovered or
touching it. So now we're going to get even more specific question
about that. אמר ליה רב מרי לרב פפא, amar lei Rav Mari
le-Rav Pappa, רב מרי Rav Mari said to רב פפא, Rav Pappa,
שער היוצא בבגדו מהו? se'ar hayotzei bevigdo mahu? Let's say a pubic
hair is somehow poking out of your garment—one wonders how that happened
if you had a toga, you didn't have like pants with a
zipper, but okay—what's the story? Is that considered ערוה erva or not
for for them for you to say you know ברכות brachos and
שמע shema in even if it's your own? So קרא עליה, kara
aleih, שער שער, se'ar se'ar, he said hair, hair! Which basically רש״י
Rashi means like he dismissed it. It's like it's not meaningful. What?
Sometimes hair is just hair. Okay, anyway, so that is not ערוה.
erva. So ערוה erva is really literally only the genitals themselves, not
even the pubic hair by itself. So אמר רבי יצחק, amar Rabi
Yitzchak, טפח באשה ערוה. tefach be-ishah ervah. Now we are doing this
shift from this whole discussion a minute ago, which was just the
genitals, to really broadening it, but here it's about somebody else and
it's about sexual thoughts, and this becomes then the big broadening of
of this category. So רבי יצחק Rabi Yitzchak says an uncovered A
handbreadth of a woman is considered an ערוה. ervah. למאי, L'mai, for
what הלכה? halacha? אילימא לאיסתכולי בה, Eilema l'istakulei bah, whether it's permitted
to gaze upon it, for a man to gaze, right, which generally
means like sort of a sexual gaze? ואמר רב ששת, V'amar Rav
Sheshet, so רב ששת Rav Sheshet says, למה מנה הכתוב תכשיטין שבחוץ
עם תכשיטין שבפנים, lama manah hakatuv tachshitin shebachutz im tachshitin shebifnim, why
did the verse when it speaks about the sort of jewelry that
they brought back from Moab mention things that were worn on the
outside together with things that were worn, you know, underneath the clothes
and according to some even in the genital area itself? ולומר לך,
V'lomar lach, to tell you, כל המסתכל באצבע קטנה של אשה, kol
hamistakel b'etzba ktana shel isha, anybody again assuming man that gazes even
at the pinky of a woman כאילו מסתכל במקום התורף k'ilu mistakel
b'makom hatoraf is like looking at the actual, you know, pubic area,
genital area itself. So if it's about sexual gaze, you can't have
sexual gaze on any part of a woman's body whether it's a
טפח tefach or not, even a pinky, pinky is smaller than a
טפח. tefach. So it's wrong for men to have sexual gaze at
women. Now of course, the גמרא's Gemara concern was not the sort
of objectifying of women and sexual gaze as a way of sort
of in terms of how it made women into sex objects, the
גמרא's Gemara concern was about men's sexual thought and it didn't want
men to be having illicit sexual thoughts, but either way it says
you're not supposed to be looking at other women sexually. So if
it's about that, it doesn't matter how much, you're not supposed to
be doing it. It doesn't matter what part of the body. Doesn't
matter what part of the body. אלא באשתו לקריאת שמע. Ela b'ishto
l'Kriat Shema. It's a man's wife and it's about קריאת שמע. Kriat
Shema. So it's his wife, so A, because it's his wife, we're
not concerned as much about illicit sexual thoughts, you know, they're I
mean, you know, they're more used
to one another and their bodies.
So
and the problem is even if you're not gazing at it but
the saying of the שמע Shema in the presence. So this gets
to the issue about the saying of שמע Shema or saying of
ברכות brachot or whatever in the presence of ערוה. ervah. Now the
question becomes here again the issue of is it ערוה ervah because
of objectively? We just got through a whole thing saying it's just
the genital areas or is it ערוה ervah because of הרהור? hirhur?
And the פוסקים poskim say it's all ערוה ervah because of הרהור.
hirhur. The way you see this is two ways. Number one is
they say it does not apply to parts of the body that
are normally uncovered and if you're in certain you know and those
so because they're not הרהור, hirhur, you know sexual thoughts, one person
you know man does not become aroused if it's a normal thing
that's normally uncovered. Number one. Number two is if that it's only
about sort of cross-sex, meaning if a woman can say שמע Shema
in the room with another woman who has a טפח tefach uncovered
and so on. It's so it's not about objective ערוה. ervah. It
is about the it is about, you know, a concern about leading
towards sexual thoughts and that's inappropriate in the context of saying the
שמע. Shema. So there really are then three categories. There's objective ערוה
ervah which has nothing to do with sexual thoughts which is even
if your own ערוה ervah is exposed, genitals, you don't say ברכות
brachot or if you're touching them and so on. Number two is
another person's body that could lead to sexual thoughts and that's the
discussion here about the woman's hair which we'll get to, the woman's
singing voice, the woman's part of the exposed body and that's a
problem about leading to sexual thoughts. And then there's a third problem
about intentionally sexually gazing a man at a woman which is always
inappropriate regardless of what part of the body and how much of
the body and so on. Okay, so those are the three categories.
It's very important to have them clear because they are often, you
know, lumped together and confused. So now the גמרא Gemara continues it
says like this. אמר רב חסדא שוק באשה ערוה. Amar Rav Chisda:
Shok b'isha ervah. A שוק shok for a woman is an ערוה.
ervah. Now what is a שוק? shok? So most if you look
at most of these צניעות tzniut books, right, well at least the
ones in the modern Orthodox community, I don't know how many the
non-Orthodox community have, but anyway you look at like the משנה ברורה
Mishna Berura whatever the story is that a שוק shok is a
thigh and that says and therefore you can you dress up to
your knees because it's only a problem about exposing your thigh. Well
a שוק shok actually is not a thigh, a שוק shok is
a calf and it's very clear that that's what a שוק shok
is. So it says that that is an ערוה. ervah. I'll get
back to the significance of that in a minute. שנאמר, Shene'emar, the
פסוק pasuk says גלי שוק עברי נהרות, gali shok ivri neharot, uncover
your שוק, shok, your calf, right your legs, the lower legs and
there walk through the rivers. So obviously you're uncovering your lower legs
to walk through the rivers. וכתיב תגל ערותך Uchtiv tegal ervatech and
the next verse says your ערוה ervah has now been exposed וגם
תראה חרפתך v'gam tera'eh cherpatech your nakedness, your embarrassment has been shown.
So you see that a שוק shok is considered an ערוה. ervah.
I'm going to read a couple of these and then I'll step
back and discuss. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says קול באשה
ערוה, kol b'isha ervah, a woman's voice is ערוה. ervah. שנאמר כי
קולך ערב ומראך נאוה, Shene'emar: ki kolech areiv umarech naveh, because your
voice is pleasing and your appearance is comely. So therefore you see
that it is something that is sort of sexually arousing. אמר רב
ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, said רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, שער באשה ערוה,
sear b'isha ervah, woman's hair's an ערוה. ervah. שנאמר שערך כעדר העזים,
Shene'emar: se'arech k'eder ha'izim, your hair is like the flock of the
goats. So again it somehow means that it is, you know, arousing
and beautiful and therefore it is a concern, it is an ערוה
ervah concern. So the first thing to share with you, which is
a great פשט Pshat *pshat* that Wendy Zierler told us, shared with
me about her read of this, which is it's not just saying
שיר השירים *Shir HaShirim* to say look these things are beautiful so
therefore they're ערוה *ervah*. It's a play on words. Every single one
of the פסוקים *psukim* have a word that is either ערוה *ervah*
or very close to ערוה *ervah*. Right? גלי שוק עברי נהרות *Givi
shok ivri naharot* already עברי *ivri* and ערוה *ervah*, even though even
the next verse even says תגל ערבתך *hagal ervatach*, but even right
there's עברי נהרות *ivri naharot*. By the by the case of קול
*kol*, it's קולך ערב *kolech arev*, so you just rearrange letters of
ערב *arev* ערב... or not ערב *arev*, you don't rearrange them, ערוה
*ervah*, right? And שערך כעדר העזים *sa'arech k'eder ha'izim* so עדר *eder*
ערוה *ervah*. That's a little bit more of a of a push,
but you sort of get that it's a similar type of a
sound. Anyway, so that's one thing. Just literarily what's going on here.
Now, the other thing is the question about what's the implication of
all of this? So in this context, the implication was about sexual
thoughts and saying of the שמע Shema *Shma*. So one important point
to say and this has to do with that whole big thing
that came a few months ago with you know with בית שמש
*Beit Shemesh* הגאון פרץ *Hagona Peretz* and so on is that based
on this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has led to this explosion of the
צניעות tzniut *tzniut* industry where it is dictating to women how much
they have to cover of their bodies because of this גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. So you have to figure out well what שוק *shok*? Does
it mean the calf and then you have to have dresses down
to your ankles? Does it mean thigh? So it can go up
to your knee. You know and all of this becomes then the
woman's obligation to cover their bodies based on this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
But what's very clear from as you've seen that's not what this
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is talking about. This גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is talking
about if it's visible about can you be saying קריאת שמע Krias
Shema *Krias Shma* in the same room? Is it a concern about
having sexual thoughts? And if you look at the פוסקים Poskim, *poskim*,
you know to the most they're able to say about a why
a woman has to cover her body is that it shouldn't you
know cause the man to be having illicit sexual thoughts. But you
know what? It's the man's primary responsibility in this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
You never have the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* saying that that's woman's primary.
It doesn't mean women should go around dressed provocatively but in terms
of like how much you have to be concerned you know that
some man might have sexual thoughts that is not the concern of
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* as women's issues. It's men's issues about looking
at women and about saying שמע *Shma* in the same room even
if you're not intentionally gazing at women that way because it leads
to sexual thoughts. So that's point one. Now point number two is
because of these גמרות *Gemarot*, there's a question about as I said
is it an issue about sexual thoughts? And then there's a culture,
you know how much is it something that is already normally something
that we encounter sort of puts limits on the on what is
the problem. So the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* for example already say you
know that if women you know they don't they don't have to
cover their faces. That's a טפח Tefach, *tefach*. Why don't they say
you have to cover your face you have to have a veil?
Oh things that are normally uncovered are not a problem. And that's
by the way the answer to the issue about the שוק *shok*.
Right? The practice was that women were not wearing ankle-length dresses. They
were wearing dresses down to their knee. So the פוסקים Poskim *poskim*
had to say one minute but the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says שוק
*shok* and a שוק *shok* is even the calf. Oh so then
they reinterpreted שוק *shok* to mean the thigh. To mean the thigh
and therefore that was the thing. But that's not the answer. The
answer is the גמרא Gemara? *Gemara* does mean the calf but the
point is that it's based on what is normally you know exposed
and not not normally exposed. So in a society in which you
know women have dresses down to their knees and not down to
their ankles so is the שוק *shok* is no longer a problem.
Now people are have anxiety around that because then what's the end
of it? What's the limit? Who do you go by? Jewish women,
non-Jewish women, modest women, not modest women? Okay so you say you
know you have to use a little שכל *sechel* and it is
true people are concerned when it's not quantifiable. But basically what is
the type of way that modest people dress and things that are
exposed in the way modest people dress is not a problem. And
that really becomes a important part of contextualizing what is being said
here. That then gets to the question about the other two that
are mentioned: hair and the voice. So the voice as well if
you look at another גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* in קידושין *Kiddushin* it says
that a woman if you even talking about speaking voice of a
woman. In certain societies men wouldn't even speak to women other than
their wives so even speaking voice is an ערוה *ervah*, right? And
if your woman is speaking in your vicinity you shouldn't be saying
שמע *Shma*. So but obviously now we have that's not an issue
and we've shifted it to mean singing voice. But the singing voice
is not in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. גמרא *Gemara* just says voice.
But because obviously in later societies voice itself wasn't a problem it
became reshaped to mean singing voice. And then becomes the issue about
what happens nowadays if you know we're somewhat inured to the singing
voices? I mean I think it depends on the context or whatever
but in some cases does it stop being a problem at least
in some cases where that does not lead to sexual thoughts? The
issue of the hair is particularly interesting because it has to work
in conversation together with the גמרא *Gemara* in כתובות Kesuvos *Ketubos* that
has it as a married woman's obligation to cover the hair. And
that's a whole question about sort of which of those גמרות *Gemarot*
you favor in terms of defining sort of you know the whole
issue about hair covering. But the upshot of all of this is
Again, it’s not talking about a woman’s obligation. In terms of a
man looking sexually at a woman, it doesn’t matter what body parts,
that’s a problem regardless. And it’s talking about what types of things
might cause sexual thoughts that’s a problem for a man to say
קריאת שמע in the context with another woman. Okay? A woman and
another woman isn’t the problem, and so on. It’s all about the
concern of sexual thoughts. And as I said, because that’s the concern,
ראשונים Rishonim, clearly say that the issue about what are the norms
of society play a very important role in qualifying what is being
said here might be, for example, say קריאת שמע while at a
Tina Turner concert. That is one application of this, yes. Sorry, I
was thinking this contextually. Most of the dress in New York, for
instance, are much more conservative than South Florida. Aha, right. So that
might also be and that is discussed in the פוסקים, Poskim which
community, you know, right, who you look at in the community and
which community you’re talking about. And there are פוסקים Poskim that talked
about, you know, when people moved from ספרד Sephard to אשכנז Ashkenaz
and different norms that were in their societies and all of that.
Is that an individual issue? Well, that’s another question as well. Some
of the issues in the גמרא about הרהורים, Hirhurim, according to some
ראשונים, is always just about you personally and never has any type
of parameters. This גמרא does seem to somewhat be giving parameters, טפח,
שיער, Se'ar, etc. So what the פוסקים Poskim do is they say,
okay, there might be objective parameters we try to apply, but we’re
going to first understand how they play out in a particular context.
But what you’re saying is no parameters, everybody decides for himself. That
is a possibility, but is that what קול אישה ערווה, Kol Isha
Ervah, you know, might be saying? It's usually uncovered. Right. Well, I
actually do think that the קול אישה ערווה Kol Isha Ervah nowadays,
even if you assume it to be contextual, it’s very hard to
say, you know, you could say, okay, you know, like here’s the
issue. Can, even assuming like the issue of hair covering in the
גמרא in כתובות Kesuvos. doesn’t change based on context, you know, for
married women, which is I think פשט of the גמרא in כתובות.
Kesuvos, So married women are supposed to cover their hair. That doesn’t
mean that a man can’t say שמע in front of a woman’s
uncovered hair. Every, the ערוך השולחן, Aruch HaShulchan, the משנה ברורה, Mishna
Berurah, all, like almost all the פוסקים say you go out in
the street, you see women’s uncovered hair all the time. It’s not
sexually arousing, so it’s not a problem. Whether it’s a woman’s obligation
to cover her hair, that’s a discussion in the גמרא in כתובות,
Kesuvos? a married woman. Whether it’s a problem for a man being
aroused or whatever, that’s not an issue because that’s the norm. Okay.
So a lot of these things do change, but your point that
everybody gets to decide by themselves, you know, I think that’s hard
to, I understand the issue about קול אישה ערווה, Kol Isha Ervah,
about singing voices, because that I do think different people have very
different reactions to and it’s hard to define some parameters. The norm
about all those things, I know. But that’s the issue with the
הלכה, Halacha, meaning הלכה Halacha doesn’t like to say you figure it
out for yourself. הלכה Halacha likes to have quantifiable rules. The חידוש
Chiddush here is that we’re in a case where we’ve somewhat quantified
it, but we’re prepared to redefine the parameters based on context. But
when that, it’s very rare that we’re prepared to completely sort of
just abandon any parameters and let everybody decide for themselves. That’s not
how a legal system, you know, tends to work. Yes. I’m just
wondering if women who are married have to cover their hair for
sexual reasons, it’s kind of strange, isn’t it? Because what’s more beautiful
than a young maiden who isn’t married and her hair? Right. So
actually it’s not clear that a woman covers her hair because of
ערווה. Ervah. That’s what I said. How does this גמרא work in
conversation with the גמרא in כתובות? Kesuvos A woman might cover her
hair as a sign of being married and as a sign of,
you know, that this type of, it’s, you know, some anthropologists have
actually said that it’s not just a Jewish society that married women
cover their hair and that hair is very alluring and it catches
the eye, you know, sort of waves and whatever. So if a
woman is single she wants to catch the eye of young men,
right? And then when she’s married, you know, a married woman should
not be trying to catch the eye of other men. So it
might have nothing to do, you know, with sexual thoughts. It has
to do with a relationship to one’s, you know, husband. And so
that is very true that the גמרא in כתובות Kesuvos could be
very different from this גמרא, which is about a concern of sexual
thoughts. Okay. He said it was really when they were talking about
cosmetics, they were talking about, yeah, but you know, again, it’s a
question about how, first of all, there are certain, you know, I
think hair covering can be a very clear sort of visible societal
norm. Whereas, you know, what? Like only unmarried women can wear cosmetics
and not married women, or, you said this, which גמרא? The issue,
but if the point, if the point was to restrict women so
they should not be attractive or alluring to other men after they’re
married, the restriction seems like it’s going much further than, it could
be, you know, I mean, I think we should be happy that
there’s a certain visibleness to it. Anyway, we can discuss, yes, you
know, if a woman wears a wig. Right, that's, yeah, the wig
is a whole issue. Okay, look, we’re way into כתובות now. That’s
about a year and a half. If the reference to this social,
societal norm, yeah, is the implication here that we should be moving
a societal norm or exceeding a societal norm? Yeah, there is that
גמרא. If the societal norm is based on sort of the modest
segment of society, which is what פוסקים assume, then there's no assumption
that you have to go beyond that. Okay? So that is correct.
Can I just add one point? To this day, State of Israel
at the כותל Kotel actually enforced all these things for women and
men, they don't let you דאווען daven together. Right. They have the
government pays these modesty women who are paid by the government to
bring these שמאַטעס, shmattes, you know, for women to cover their legs,
their arms, or whatever, so that this little paragraph is already being
enforced by the state of... I understand. These three lines of גמרא,
the impact these three lines have had, you know, throughout Jewish society,
not you know all the צניעות attitudes and all of that is
like, you know, incalculable. Let's just read to the end of the
דף daf here. We'll end with the bottom of the דף. daf.
אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rebi Chanina, אני ראיתי את רבי, ani raisi
es Rebi, I saw רבי Rebi שתלה תפילין, shetal tfillin, that he
now we're back to תפילין, tfillin, that basically there was a peg
and he suspended his תפילין tfillin from the peg. So presumably it
means like, you know, the של ראש, shel rosh, you know, is
like a loop, so the loop of the back loop was there
and the box of the תפילין tfillin was hanging down. Was on
the peg. מיתיבי Meiseivei ask you this: התולה תפיליו חייו? hatoleh tfillav
chayav? If somebody sort of hangs his תפילין, tfillin, his life will
be suspended in front of him. So pretty harsh, but of course
it's a way of saying don't do it, it's disrespectful to the
תפילין. tfillin. ודורשי חמורות אמרו, Vedorshei chamuros amru, those that interpret חמורות
chamuros רש"י Rashi says means like sort of like knotted up things,
you know, puzzles, explain the following פסוק: pasuk: והיו חייך תלאים לך
מנגד, vehayu chayecha tluyim lecha mineged, your life will be suspended in
front of you, one of the curses in the תורה. Torah. זה
התולה תפיליו, Zeh hatoleh tfillav, that's what happens if you suspend your
תפילין, tfillin, because תפילין tfillin is your life, תורה Torah is כי
הם חייך ואורך ימיך, ki heim chayecha ve'orech yamecha, so if you're
suspending your תפילין, tfillin, you're hanging it on a peg, bad business.
So לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא ברצועה הא בקציצה,
ha beretzuah ha bektzitza, if you suspend it by the strap and
the box is hanging down, that's not respectful. If you somehow suspend
it by the קציצה ktzitza which is the box, I don't know
how you'd suspend a box on a peg, maybe it's a rectangular
peg that has actually a flat part to it, so you're not
so much suspending it, it's more like you're putting it on a
shelf, but at least the strap is what's hanging down, that's not
a problem. ואיבעית אימא Vi'isayma לא שנא רצועה ולא שנא קציצה אסור,
lo shna retzuah velo shna ktzitza assur, either way it's forbidden to
suspend it. וכי תלא ליה רבי בקיסתא תלא ליה, Veki tal lei
Rebi bekistah talvei, he, when did he suspend it? He suspended it
actually בקיסתא, bekistah, in its bag. So what? It was covered. It
was covered, and he, right, it was in its bag, and its
bag was what he was hanging on the hook. אי הכי מאי
למימרא? Ihachi mai lemre? If so it should be obvious? No, מהו
דתימא בעי הנחה כספר תורה mahu d'seima ba'ei hanacha k'Sefer Torah קמשמע
לן. kamashmalan. No, because let's say you have a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah and you have that wrapped in its mantel, you put it
flat on a table, you don't like, you know, suspend it from
something, it doesn't stop being a ספר תורה Sefer Torah because it's
covered. So here too, you might think that even though, this is
what we discussed before, even after the תפילין tfillin are wrapped in
the bag, to what degree does it make it as though, you
know, they're not present anymore or not? So it says at least
for the הלכה halacha that you don't have to lay them flat
and you can suspend them, that's okay once they're in their bag.
Okay?